so why all the confusion why are these
poor undergraduates being taught all
these different things in textbooks
every website you go to has a different
answer every coach you talk to seems to
disagree or argue and every potential
expert says they know something
different
well i think if we go over these next
couple of slides you're going to
understand why the confusion exists
and you'll be able to rest easy by with
knowing the fact there is no confusion
okay so let's dive into this just a
little bit
what we do know is based on our
different
typing methods
if you look at the studies that have
used either histochemistry or
homogeneous gels
you're going to find arguing back and
forth about whether or not fiber types
change with training
however
every single study
ever done
that's used single fiber
gel electrophoresis
which allows you to actually accurately
identify and type those hybrids
every single one of those studies
is in agreement
so if you wonder why the confusion it
simply comes down to a methodology issue
look back at your textbook
look back at the blog you read or
whatever you read that said there was
some confusion about this i guarantee
you
if you read the papers they're citing
they use either histochemistry or gel
homogenous or worse yet they compare the
results from the two
and you know what i don't blame you for
this by the way let me make sure that
that's clear because it's not fair in
fact even in a recent
published
literature review
the authors wrote a little passage that
made me pull my freaking hair out in
fact it's the reason why i made this
talk
right let me let me read this verbatim
so that i don't misquote them
ready quote
findings opposing alterations in fiber
type do exist thus
the contention that exercise elicits a
shift in fiber type remains
unsubstantiated at least
in part
unquote
no it's not
in fact if you look at this study and
i'm not naming the authors on purpose
here
i'm not trying to throw them under the
bus in fact i know several of them and
they're fantastic people and researchers
but this is a real problem in science
how did this get through none of their
studies at all not a single one of their
studies
used the single fiber method even though
at the time
two or three dozen papers had been
published using that methodology in fact
the majority of their studies were over
20 years old i can't believe that this
got through so i don't blame you as a
researcher i don't blame you as a
student i don't blame you as someone
who's not in this field at all but just
is geeking out right now how could you
not be possibly confused when only a few
people in the world
understand what's going on here
so we need to set a higher standard
there
if you look at the basic results whether
you're using histochemistry or gels and
you compare that to the single fiber
stuff i want to set you up so that you
understand a basic fiber type profile so
most people in most muscles are
in the vl i should say the vasos
lateralis if you use either yellow or
you'd have something like 50 of your
fibers type 1 30 percent type 2a and 20
type 2x it probably be reported as type
2b but you know i know that it's 2x
right
gotcha right
if you look at the gels we see something
that which is very similar right forty
percent
uh the single fiber gels forty percent
type one which is close to fifty percent
here
about forty percent two way
which is close about twenty percent uh
hybrids combined which means about ten
percent one two and ten percent to a two
x
and in fact
in these
look at that
interesting now you may pick this up
earlier and i've been specifically
avoiding it until now if you did good
for you you're clever little devil
okay so we see a very different fiber
toe pro fiber type profile
in some aspects but overall looks pretty
similar
and if you looked at the studies
that have been done in here what you're
probably going to find in general is a
conclusion that okay
with exercise training we don't see a
change in the type ones
we see an increase in two ways and a
consummate decrease in two x's in fact i
still see this being published in brand
new textbook every year
that quote
if you do training
you decrease your two x's
i see this all the time with people that
and i'm bless their heart i'm not
blaming them because this is really
confusing
i'm sure i make similar mistakes when i
talk about bone or nerve or things like
that because that's not my field so man
i'm really not blaming you at all i'm
really trying to help
but i see this all the time people say
well when you train your two exes go
away
you're referring to studies that are 30
years old
in fact we see something totally
different in all of the new studies how
can something go away when it doesn't
exist
it's not clear yet let me show you
all right
what you would see here
in all of these studies is that we see
changes up and down
right all of your fiber types change
with training when we have this
specificity in typing
so why the discrepancy
let's take a look
a couple of really clever studies should
help us answer this question
so what these two studies did is they
took individual muscle fibers and they
cut them down the middle and split them
one half of the fiber came over here
and got analyzed for its fiber type via
histochemistry the other half of the
identical muscle fiber was cut and put
through our single fiber electrophoresis
process
so what they able what the researchers
were able to do then is come back and
say okay this exact muscle fiber when
typed with histochemistry was this
and when typed with single fiber
electrophoresis was this in other words
are the two methods
valid are they telling us the same
information or not
well what they saw was okay when we
typed all of the fibers in the study
using the histochemistry method
we got about 50 of the fibers were type
ones about 25 or 2a or something like
that remember maybe more like 30
and then 20 percent was type 2x which is
very similar to the distribution i
showed you a second ago right is what we
would predict
but the exact same fibers type the other
method
came out to be more like this
something more like twenty five percent
type one
oh ten to twenty percent one two a
maybe twenty percent two way thirty or
thirty five percent to a two x and
almost none or pure two x's
so here's what you could identify or
infer from this
what happens is a major number of the
fibers typed with histochemistry are
actually
hybrid fibers misclassified
remember histo it's black white and then
gray grayish gray or error well you have
to take some of those grays and say this
is a
type one this is a lightly this is an
opaque an eggshell white if you will
we'll call it a white
well now what we see is when we increase
the fidelity or accuracy of our measure
we say no no no that's not a white
that's a 1 2a
ah interesting
this does two
very important things
number one
why is it we can't find that fiber types
are changing with training
which of our fiber types were the ones
that changed the most with training
the hybrids right
well if i have a fiber we'll call it a
type one and it is a one two hey one two
a meaning i'm untrained right it should
be a one-two-way if i start training
that should convert into being a pure
two or a pure type one based on what
i've i've just described right
but if my pre-measurement before my
training study is done and i mistype
that one two way as a type one
then i go and do my endurance training
it's now being converted into a type one
but i've already typed it as a type one
so it's a one before the study and it's
a one after the study no change
when in actuality it did change
all right so i think right here this is
a great example or a great explanation
of why all those early studies that use
cystochemistry
came up with these mixed conclusions
or most specifically said hey ones don't
change well that's because so many
people have so many one two a's and so
many of them were being misclassified as
a pure one or a pure 2a of course you
don't see any change
we see that being also extremely evident
with the two a two x's
remember how a slide ago i told you with
histochemistry we generally say that
your two x's go away with training what
we now know is those two x's are
actually two a two x's that are
mis-typed
and what happens to two a two x's when
you start training they go away right
they differentiate into becoming
probably pure two a's
so this right here explains very clearly
both of our initial problems why is it
these things are arguing why are we not
seeing a change then all of a sudden we
started seeing a change when we switched
to more accurate methodologies and two
why is it that they report
some of the reports say that you go down
in your two x's but some of them show no
two x's
this is why the confusion exists
if you just pay attention to the
methodology you find this answer
and it also brings up something else
very very interesting
why is it we don't see many of these
pure 2x's
hmm
well in fact what's actually happening
here if we could summarize is
several studies across several labs
across the world have shown that
actually less than one out of every 1
fibers are a pure 2x
in fact in my laboratory we have typed
several thousand fibers and i found only
a small handful of pure 2xs
we never see them
they're just not available in normal
human physiology other than a few
exceptions
we have seen some older individuals that
are saying maybe two or three percent 2x
maybe up to five percent but not much
more than that
and your young healthy populations
almost never
in fact
here's where stuff got really crazy
if we look at a normal distribution like
we've been saying using our single fiber
electrophoresis maybe 40 50 type 1
20 30 40 2a and then maybe 10 15 20
total hybrids i'm just making these
numbers up
well i got to be a part of several years
ago a really interesting study that took
a muscle biopsy of a world champion
sprinter this is a world record holder
and the
60 i think 110 meter hurdles
well
for the most part like i said less than
1.1 actually 0.1 percent of all fibers
are pure 2x in our normal population
well this particular sprinter was
actually sort of like what we would
expect
he had less he had very few numbers of
pure type ones which is very normal he
had a lot of these two ways not too many
hybrids
we had taken this biopsy or sorry we
hadn't the biopsy had been done um
several years after the athlete was over
competing so he wasn't necessarily super
trained
um
it probably moderately at best so he did
have a few of these hybrids but it was
maybe just a few years after his his
world record performances
but what shocked us
was that
right this particular athlete had 24
percent pure 2x fibers
to my knowledge not another athlete or a
person the planet a healthy person i
should say
has had that many two x's so quite
literally
he was an x-men
get it and what's particularly
interesting about this is if we look
back at the problems i talked about
earlier
what are the type of athletes that we're
missing from this fiber type equation
we've done excessive extensive research
on your endurance athletes but we have
no information on anaerobic athletes and
absolutely not on fast athletes
and if we consider what it means to be a
fast twitch
fiber
that quite literally is speed right the
difference between a fast twitch and
slow switch is speed of twitch it's not
even necessarily size which we'll talk
about in a second are power it's speed
so to me it makes the most sense to say
well you want to see people on the other
end of the speed spectrum you've already
typed the slowest people
why not type the fastest people
hasn't been done yet
right so
i always get this follow-up question
here at this point is okay well if no
one ever has these pure 2xs what's the
point of them
i honestly don't know we could speculate
a few reasons why we think they exist
because we only see them in really two
populations this crazy world record
holder sprinter
and then people that have actually had
their spine or other major issues where
a muscle has been de-innervated for
decades or years at least
some of these folks have 60 70 percent
2x's
what most people think is that it's a
little bit more metabolically efficient
to have a fast twitch fiber it's too
much energy to keep these slow twitch
fibers that are packed with mitochondria
you need a lot of
metabolism need a lot of oxygen around
to stay to stay
surviving and so when the fiber is about
to die it may be transitions its way
from slow to fast all the way down to 2x
so 2x could be a sign of dying and this
is also why if you do have marginal
amounts of 2x if you do engage in any
activity they go away
the case with this particular world
sprinter though
i don't know
what's using bolt or justin gatlin look
like
i don't know
okay so to summarize everything our
final points here before we hit some
final conclusions why did all the
confusion exist here
it simply came down to a lack of
sensitive sensitivity in the fiber
typing methods once we cleared that up
we seem to have no more confusion
the other major cause of confusion was
that misclassification of fibers
specifically the misclassification of
the 1 2a
and 2a2x hybrids
and the misclassification of those pure
2x fibers
as we wrap up this final
this talk i wanted to end on a little
bit of a positive note
and to talk about the future a little
bit and this is what i'll actually call
my call for action
the reason we have so many problems in
this areas is because people aren't
interested in enough of these questions
now what i mean is people are interested
but they're not the right people
are interested so what ends up happening
is we have a ton of people out there and
i don't even know who's listening but
probably some of you
are really interested in say the sport
performance aspect of muscle physiology
so perhaps you're a coach you could talk
all day about different training systems
and how one's a little bit better for
power production one's better for
hypertrophy or something
and then on the other end of this
continuum we have people that are
excellent muscle scientists
right so they could take an isolated
cell from a petri dish or they could
take a fiber from an animal and they
could run a bunch of really impressive
and complicated cellular molecular
analyses but what we don't have is
anybody in the middle
we don't have any people like like you
see my four students here who know the
practical side they they have their cscs
certification they are themselves
athletes they work directly with
athletes but they also work in the
laboratories and i think the reason for
that is is
people that are coaches get too
intimidated
by this science and the sophistication
and then the people that are that are
scientists
either don't have an appreciation for
the application
or never really trained don't really
work out don't really understand it or
care
well i want to break both of those
things because like in fact i know that
this stuff although it sounds
complicated and sophisticated
you can do it too
right you see these people here all my
four students that are running
experiments not a single one of them had
a chemistry class before they came into
my laboratory they're all graduate
students they came from different
backgrounds one of them is a yogi one of
them came from another country some of
them have came from different fields
entirely athletic training
biology you name it
right we can teach
you
anything you need to it's if it's not
that complicated most people come into
our lab and they think like wow this is
actually not that much more difficult
than baking a pie
making a cake it's not that complicated
so those of you that are maybe hedging
yourself toward the practitioner side
but you think this stuff is really
fascinating and interesting and you're
an undergraduate or a high schooler or
even in graduate school
don't sell yourself short
i barely had a three-point gpa as an
undergrad and i'm the director of the
biochemistry and molecular exercise
physiology laboratory i never took
organic chemistry i didn't take
biochemistry until i was a phd student i
have a phd in bioenergetics
right so i don't want to portray any
false sense of this is too complicated
oh my god this is so sophisticated well
we try to make it complicated but it's
fun and any of you can do it so if you
are all inclined i really think we need
more people that understand the
practical side to get into it
we just don't have many people so that's
my call to action and if i can help you
anyway
along the way please let me know i
really love it when we get people that
really understand performance
in this field of cellular and molecular
biology
to summarize our entire talk now that
i've got off that soapbox
all right we have this initial question
at the very beginning right we have
these black fibers and we've got these
white fibers and these slow twitch
infastration we wanted to know can they
change with training well i hope we've
answered the question that absolutely
they can doesn't mean it will but we
certainly can and it can happen in
normal situations
we also have identified that our fibers
could probably be somewhere in the
middle so we've got black white and gray
and then a bunch of things and
we also need to understand that
your muscle is tremendously plastic so
depending on what you've heard a lot of
people will say things like hey the
first four to six to eight weeks of any
training program all of the adaptations
are neurological
that's not true at all
certainly a lot of the adaptations are
neurological but don't you give all that
credit to the stupid nervous system
muscle has some stuff too muscle is a
job adapting everything you do matters
every sleep
recovery training nutrition choice you
make
influences the way muscle adapts i would
argue it is the most plastic most
adaptable system in your entire body
we've picked up changes in fiber types
in tremendously short durations
right
so give muscle some credit and realize
that everything you do matters it sees
it and it changes because of it
we started off four or five decades ago
with all these different fiber types
and as i mentioned
hours ago right in 1971 they were
already saying things like you know what
this is really just a big continuum
we've got slow and fast and everything's
somewhere in the middle and in fact
we'll go back to a quote that i told you
earlier i love that i still love
fiber types are simply too dynamic
and flexible
so fiber typing is clearly important
but we do need to recognize that muscle
function goes far beyond simply fiber
type
in fact there are very famous people in
this field that study muscle function at
a very high level and they'll say things
like fiber type doesn't matter well i
think i've made my case now that it does
matter but i will grant them it's not
everything i can't predict 100 of your
vertical jump ability your max dead lift
your one mile sprint time simply based
on your fiber type it's an important
consideration but there are other things
and we're not going to get into them now
but this is one quick example
we have to realize that single fiber
function
changes what i mean by that is i'll take
an individual muscle fiber and we'll
call it a fast and slow one like we've
been doing since the very beginning
well those fibers produce a certain
amount of power or force per contraction
but that force and power can change over
time
just like at the whole muscle level
right
you know it's possible to get stronger
and more powerful without necessarily
adding any more muscle mass right
well if i asked you why does that happen
or how is that possible you would all
say well it's neurological
well it is in part
but what we know is the contractile
ability of the fibers changes
independent of fiber type change and
signs
so if for example if we had a fast rich
fiber here and a slow twitch fiber there
and they produced some random amount of
power
after some sort of training it doesn't
matter i'm just making arbitrary units
here this is not a particular study i'm
just showing you a concept
after say 8 10 12 weeks of study of
training the amount of power each one of
those individual fibers can produce
goes up
so independent of the slow turning into
a fast its single fiber function
can improve right we're just starting to
explore this area there's been some
great work done in the past but we need
a lot more and we need to expand our
horizons in terms of what we're looking
at
right so some other considerations that
that would play into whole muscle
function are things like metabolic
capacity we started off our talk talking
about how the original way to
differentiate fiber types was enzymatic
profiles well we need to explore that
area some more that certainly can play a
role in in whole muscle function
the percent of the area occupied like we
mentioned i don't necessarily know that
performance is more or less dictated by
distribution or percent area occupied
contraption fiber function like we just
mentioned and other things like that are
beyond muscle themselves things like the
extracellular matrix this would be sort
of the connective tissue around your
fibers muscle how that works into a
tendon and and the force production or
transfer abilities of the tendon and
collagen
bone penation angle biomechanics
neurological considerations
all of that functions and we haven't
even got into sports psychology
motivation
or things like that so
human performance is extremely complex
this this does explain a portion of it
and what obviously i think a very
interesting portion of it
but i am well aware and happy to
acknowledge that it's not everything
on that note
what we generally recognize is a couple
of things
in general
your fast twitch fibers different than
most people think are actually not
bigger
than your slow twitch fibers
in fact
they're simply faster
so my colleague dr bagley is working on
this and it will probably honestly take
us years before we can publish this so
you can rake me over the coals now if
you want
but we generally don't see
the fibers being different per fiber
type per size what we see different
is the contractile velocity
unless you're specifically trained so
someone who does a lot of strength
training resistance exercise
they probably is some fiber type
specific hypertrophy happening there
their fast switch fibers probably will
be bigger than their slow twitch but
we've seen that on the other end of the
spectrum as well high level endurance or
just highly trained
someone who's done a lot of endurance
training their slow twitch fibers are
probably bigger than their fast switch
fibers
again i know i'm telling you we don't
have the proof now
we have the numbers in the lab it's it's
literally going to take us years to get
that stuff out but trust me when i say
that
all right
but perhaps this is why we really didn't
see any of these differences in those 2x
until we tell that that world-class
sprinter was biopsied
from that one lab
so
just stuff to consider in the future um
fiber types probably explain fast more
than anything
of course we know that
power is a function
of speed right the power is force times
velocity so perhaps this is why we see
that and if we studied more people that
were further down the fast spectrum
perhaps we understand more about muscle
function
we know these things in case you are
wondering i brought this up several
times and i will give you some numbers
the speed is different
a lot different in fact that's the most
significant difference between these
fiber types is their speed of
contraction
because that is a part of power power is
different as well but probably not as
different as the speed
and strength
not so much either
what we generally say is your your type
two a's are somewhere about two to five
times as fast as your type ones with
your two x's when we can find them
somewhere in the neighborhood of ten to
fifteen times faster
than your type ones
it's really important for me that we go
back all the way to the beginning to
wrap up this massive video
we have to recognize our own limitations
our own faults and mistakes
as paramount and unbelievably as
impressive as huxley and huxley's 1954
description of the sliding film theory
was
we're only now starting to realize
you know what maybe they're actually a
little bit wrong
but that's not to demean them or insult
them what they this is arguably one of
the greatest discoveries of muscle
function in human history
but it's not perfect
and i expect you to understand the same
thing about the talk i just gave about
muscle fiber types i told you about as
much information as as i know on muscle
fiber types but i fully recognize
i'm sure some of that's wrong there
might be some folks out there right now
that have done studies that are in this
field that say actually we're finding
something different or we disagree with
this point and i would love to hear it i
promise you something in that talk i
just gave is very wrong
normally probably right now but
certainly 10 20 30 years from now all
this talk will be completely different
so the best way i can describe this with
this part of physiology or really any
aspect of physiology or nutrition for
that matter is this is as we understand
it now this is our best and most current
information
when we learn more stuff
will change
right so i have to to
thank dr jimmy bagley for this um his
muscle his website
musclefizlab.com is phenomenal and he's
helped me so much over the years he's a
real expert i would really encourage
if you like single fiber function if
you'd like muscle physiology like this
to check out his lab and his social
media
at dr jimmy bagley
because he's a real true expert and a
pioneer in this field
but also to recognize that you know
perhaps if anything maybe i got 80 of
this thing wrong um well probably not
but certainly something's wrong in this
maybe though i entertained you hopefully
at least i told a fun enough story that
inspired you to learn this field and
you'll spend hundreds and thousands of
hours diving into this stuff and you can
come back in
a month or a year from now and tell me
what i missed what i did wrong
ultimately that's the goal of doing all
these things i appreciate you sticking
around for this whole time hope you had
fun uh please share around and let me
know what i can do to help
peace and love y'all
you